Guide to the Samuel H. Gottscho Photographs 1930s PR 423
New-York Historical Society
Samuel H. Gottscho photographs
1930s
New-York Historical Society
Gottscho, Samuel H. (Samuel Herman), 1875-1971
PR 423
2 Linear feet in 1 flat box (12 photographs)
The collection consists of 12 vintage silver gelatin photographs taken in the early 1930s by Samuel H. Gottscho (1875-1971). Ten of the photographs, taken in 1933, are of Manhattan views. One is centered on Welfare Island (Roosevelt Island) and one is a detail of a cemetery at Gardiner's Island in East Hampton.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series, based in part on provenance:
Series I. Manhattan 1933 Views
Series II. Other Photographs
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Herman Gottscho (1875-1971) was born in Brooklyn, New York. During his early life, he practiced photography on a part-time basis, deciding to work professionally as a commercial photographer in the 1920s, around the age of 50. Respected as an architectural, landscape, and nature photographer, major collections of Gottscho's work are held by the Library of Congress and the Museum of the City of New York.
(The above note was derived from Gottscho's entry in Wikipedia.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All but one of the photographs were the gift of Elizabeth Barlow Rogers, 2021. The exception is noted at the item level in the container list.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 12 vintage silver gelatin photographs taken in the early 1930s by Samuel H. Gottscho (1875-1971). Ten of the photographs, taken in 1933, are of Manhattan views, and were originally a gift from Gottscho to a Grace Mayer. These include Gottscho's handwritten titles and captions. Generally, these photographs were taken either from an elevated height and show downward sweeping views of the city and wide angles of skylines, buildings, and streets, or ground level, upward looking views of buildings and other features of the urban built environment.
In addition to the above set, the collection holds two other photographs: one looks east from Manhattan toward Welfare Island (Roosevelt Island) and Queens, and a second is a detailed view within a cemetery on Gardiner's Island in East Hampton, New York.
Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Roosevelt Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Gelatin silver prints.
- Series I. Manhattan 1933 Views
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists of 10 photographs of various Manhattan views, all taken by Gottscho in 1933. The specific titles are listed in the inventory below. The principal distinguishing feature of this series is that, according to the label affixed to the mats of the photographs, all were originally a "Gift from Artist to Grace Mayer (1959)."
  All have a handwritten title and some have a fuller caption by Gottscho. The container list indicates the title given, and indicates which items have a more extended caption. The photographs retain their matting and labeling from the donation to N-YHS, but they were unframed for conservation purposes.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged in the order the photographs were documented by the donor's registrar and presented to N-YHS.
  - "Ants and Beetles -- Busy Broadway at 39th [Street], New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
    Has caption with photographer comment.
  - "Central Park West Reflected in Park Lake, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "Columbus Circle from Above, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "Day S.W. [Southwest] from the River House, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "El [Elevated Train Tracks], Coenties Slip, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "From Pier 32, East River, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "Looking North from Empire State Building, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "Night from the Empire State Building toward Queens, New York", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "The New York Central Building, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
  - "The RCA Building, Rockefeller Center, New York City", 1933 (Box 1)
- Series II. Other Photographs, 1930s
  The series consists of two standalone photographs by Gottscho. They are itemized in the container list below.
  - "Gardiner's Island. Boulder in Cemetery", circa 1930 (Box 1)
    Stamped "Samuel H. Gottscho." Photograph #13704. (Transferred to this collection from the Photographer File, PR 50, in July 2021; the image had been misidentified in that collection as a cemetery on Governor's Island.)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Charles Schwartz, December 2001.
  - [Welfare Island], 1931 December 15 (Box 1)
    Stamped "Gottscho-Schleisner, Inc.", photograph #17487. Taken from an elevated height in Manhattan, the view extends across the East River, taking in much of Welfare Island (now Roosevelt Island) and Queens in the distance. The view north includes the Ed Koch Queensboro Bridge (also known as the 59th Street Bridge).
    Gift of Elizabeth Barlow Rogers, 2021.